A Guide to the Virginia Geological Survey, Records, 1834-1903
Library of Virginia
- Series II: Reports, sections, lists and field notes, 1834-1884
  - Israel Slade, 1840 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Israel Slade, 1840, Field notes. Observations along the mountains from Harpers Ferry to southwest Virginia. 3 vols. 1) Harpers Ferry to Wythe County. 158 pp. 2) Smyth and Wythe Counties. 68 pp. 3) Montgomery, Pulaski, Roanoke, Smyth, Tazewell, Washington, and Wythe Counties. 336 pp.
  - Miscellaneous, 1850-1884 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1850?, Photography of Thomas Jefferson Campbell (1786-April 13, 1850) of Tennessee, Clerk of United States House of Representatives, Thirtieth and Thirty-First Congresses (1847-1850).
    - Miscellaneous, 1852, A description of Weyer's Cave in Augusta County, Virginia. 1 vol., 11 pp.
    - Miscellaneous, 1853-1854, Thirty-eight annual report of the Board of Public Works to the General Assembly of Virginia, with the accompanying documents. January 28, 1854. 1 vol., 28 pp.
    - Miscellaneous, 185?, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C. Registry of Periodical Phenomena. Printed form, not filled in. 4 pp.
    - Miscellaneous, 1884?, Typescripts of material excerpted from earlier records. 1) List of boxes put up by Dr. Jas. B. Rogers and G.W. Boyd, 1838. 1 p. (3 copies) 2) Boxes collected in 1839. 2 pp. (2 copies) 3) Analyses unconnected with the survey, 1836. 4 pp. (3 copies) 4) Section at Scholham taken by John Gebhard, Jr., 1839. 1 p. (3 copies) 5) Springs, 1839. 3 pp. (3 copies) 6) Matinal Series, Virginia, n.d. 1 p. (3 copies) 7) Envelope, n.d. 1 item.
    - Miscellaneous, n.d., Profile of the Works on Vein no. 4. Plate 2. Shows level of the Rappahannock River. 1 p.
    - Miscellaneous, n.d., Sketch map showing Monogahela, Cheat, and Youghogany rivers. Possibly by Charles B. Hayden. 2 pp.
    - Miscellaneous, n.d., Scrap of paper and cardboard, with notes in handwriting of William B. Rogers. 2 items.
- Series III: Drawings of Russell Smith, c. 1844
  Rogers engaged Smith to execute a series of drawings of significant geological formations in Virginia for use in Rogers's projected final report on the state geological survey. There are 51 sketches on paper and cardboard, in pencil, ink, watercolors, pastels and oils.
  - Russell Smith, c. 1844 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Russell Smith, 1844, Monticello and University Va. July 4th/44. Ink. Also light pencil sketch of a fireplace and pencil sketch of U.Va. - Monticello on reverse. Albemarle.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Turner's mountain in the extreme distance. High top of left. Pencil. (Albemarle) No date.
    - Russell Smith, 1844, Interior of cavern, illuminated by torches, with "tourists." "Russell Smith 1844." Oil.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Distant Mt. Bull Pasture. Hills are Slate. "Foreground Paving Stones, grass and Accassia. Light from L.H." "Near Col. 'Bill' Dyer's." "1. White walnut. 2. Elm. 3. Buttonwood. 4. Elm. 5. Dark Linden. 6. Sycamore. 7. Water Willow." Ink. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., View of valley through gap in mountains, possibly near Waynesboro? Ink. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, 1844, Falls of the Kanowha. Russell Smith 1844. Ink.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., View across valley to cultivated mountains in distance. Ink. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Brown's Gap. N.W. by W. Ink. Undated. (Albemarle Co., p. 113)
    - Russell Smith, 1844, Looking NW. Bull Past. Mn. and Thorn Mn. No[rth] Fork Mn. Alleghany Mn. From top of Shen Mn. Dry River Gap. "Russell Smith 1844." Ink.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Pencil sketch of stream surrounded by trees. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Piney Mtn. North of Charlottesville. Ink. Undated. (Albemarle Co.)
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Black Thorn Creek. Gag's Mill. South Branch Potomac. Pencil and Ink. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, 1844, From the house of Co. Jef. Randolph. Edgehill. July 9th/44. Notes locations of Monticello, Shadwell Hill, Rivanna River, and birthplace of T. J. Ink. (e. of Charlottesville)
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Callaghan's meadow. Pencil. Undated. (Shenandoah Co., p. 308)
    - Russell Smith, 1844, Cane Hill. Augusta Cy. VA. Russell Smith 1844. Ink.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Pencil and Ink sketch of rock formation.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Ink and watercolor. House in foreground, view across valley to mountains. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Pencil sketch. River with log bridge in foreground, frame buildings on bank. Undated. Reverse: pencil portrait, woman's head and neck.
    - Russell Smith, 1844, Devil's Backbone. Crab Bottom. July 1844. "South Branch of the Potomac, Va. Russell Smith 1844." Ink.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Shenandoah mountains from Col. William Ayer's. Looking S>E>" Ink. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., North Mtn. in distance. Piney Mtn. Looking S.E. from Kaisers. Pencil. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., South fork of the south Branch of the Potomac. Pencil. Undated. Notes on reverse: No. 1 and 2. Two very large tulip trees. No. 1 over 100 feet high. 3. Black walnut. 4. Sycamore. Color of Gold. 5. Decayed sycamore also very large. The two spots on Bullpasture mountain are smooth walls of light grey Rock. The River is low, leaving in the foreground pools of water with every variety of plants. The dark shadow on Mt. falls in beautifully with the tall dark poplar and spreads out up over the mountain to the night. The general tone is dark. Principal light high up in the sky and the 2nd on the shore. Sky Constable like or English like. From the presence of so much walnut and Sycamore I see none of the cold heavy greens noticed in Cole's 2nd picture of the "Voyage of life" but all is warm and harmonizing with the shadows.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., View of mountains, looking across valley. Stunted tree in foreground. Ink. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, 1844, Rocks at the Rawly Springs on Dry River. July 1844. Pencil.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Pencil sketch of rock formation. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Cliff at Callaghan's. Pencil, ink, and watercolor. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, 1844, Russell Smith 1844. Cliff at Callaghan's, Va.: Pencil.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Cave Hill looking South West. Ink. Undated. (Page County, Luray, pp. 409-414)
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Photograph of Mr. Campbell, Clerk of the House, Washington, D.C.
  - Russell Smith, c. 1844 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Pencil and ink sketch of interior of cavern. Undated. Notes on reverse: Bright lights caused by lights reflected from the sky on wet leaves and pieces of wood; dry light in distance cool and comes over an irregular rocky sruface. It only terminates in half lights at the lower left hand corner; some bright warm lights touching the edges and lower ends of the stalactites. They being wet give in places sharp lights. Brightest and warmest light to right of dark columns on right and on he roof above them.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., View across farm lands to mountains. Ink. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Mass[anuten]Mountain from Miller's Iron Works near cave. Wheat field. Ink. Undated. (Page County, p. 408)
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Rock formation, fence and gate. Pencil and watercolor. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Stream and mountains from valley. Pencil. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., From Harsbergers [?] Jackson's River [?] and Rocks. Pencil. Undated; "Crab Bottom." Pencil. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Interior of cavern, with miscellaneous coloring notes. Watercolor. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Interior of cavern, with color key. Ink. Undated. Notes on reverse: the light and shadow of this piece is very broad and soft and the whole column is warm and rich. The middle tint is the most cool although not cold. A figure in white is necessary to produce a bright light. The celing [sic] is remarcably [sic] rich in fine stalictites [?] by small [?] of the most fantastic forms occasionally showing white cristals.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Interior of cavern. Pencil, ink, and watercolor. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Hillside rock formation. Pencil. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Rock formation on top of mountain, with view of valley. Ink. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Wooded, rocky glen with waterfall. Pencil. Undated. Notes on reverse: Water falls white and half light. Distant fall on the right hand little more than rain and of a grey colour. The rocks are of a grey yellowish colour but one [?] with light green vegetation all front of the falls. Where their have surface appears it is yellowish brown and very dark and rich in the shadows. The cliffs are grey, yellow, and slate colour. All left of the falls being light yellow and grey. That to the right is dark green and purpleish grey, almost black in places. The light is from the right and high. The trees are Buckeye, Sycamore, and Elm. Some with raies[?]. Although the work yellowish is used there is nothing yellow appearing in the whole ruin except the R.'s hat. Portions of the falls are shaded by tree tops and jutting rocks. Small portions received the sunlight and are of the brightest white.
    - Russell Smith, 1844, Cascade near the Falls of the Kanawha. Russell Smith 1844. Ink and chalk.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., View from bottom of valley across cleared fields, forest, to mountains. Ink. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., The Rivanna River looking S.E. from Col. Jefferson Randolph's. Pencil and ink. Undated. (Albemarle Co.)
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Falls or rapids, with building across river on right, mountains all around. Ink. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., View of the Blue Ridge from the Mansion of Jno. C. Carter, Esqr. Albemarle Co. Virginia. Landmarks noted: "Buck's Elbow, Turk's Gap, Pasture Fence Mtn., Browns Cave." Ink. Undated. (1875-"Profitt's" on Pigeion Mtn.)
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Continuation of same view, to right. Landmarks labeled: "Brown's Gap, Lemon's Gap." Ink. Undated. 46 and 47 together form panorama.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., View across valley to mountains, portion of collonaded house in foreground. Ink. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., View of University of Virginia and Monticello Mountain, taken from back and to the left of 1. Ink. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., View across bottom to hills, with buildings, bridge. Pencil. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., View of river or meadow, trees left and right, hills in background. Pencil. Undated.
    - Russell Smith, n.d., Rocky, wooded, river gorge. Pencil. Undated.